Hello
everyone. Welcome to True Health
Tuesdays. This is my first time, so this
is all new for me. My name is Maria Jose
Hmel and um I am so excited to be here.
Um I have been a nutritionist for many
many years. In fact, I used to be first
a I think Atante already told you this
for two Sabbaths in a row. So, if you
didn't hear my bio, I'm not going to
repeat it. Uh, you can go back to the
last two Sabbaths and hear the bio. Um,
but I used to be an engineer and then I
changed my career to nutritionist. I got
a master's in nutrition. Then I got a
master's in public health because I
think that totally reinforced the you
know public health aspects of nutrition.
Then I went ahead and got a PhD in
naturopathic health. But I absolutely uh
incorporated nutrition into that and all
the true
um remedies that come from God. So, I am
just so excited to be able to share with
you the true remedies that God has given
us in and in particular the nutrition
aspects because that is really what I
love the most. that I will try to
incorporate all of the things that God
has given us, especially those eight
gifts, eight true remedies, eight
principles of health that God has given
us in order to be healthy, to prevent
all these diseases that are the most
prevalent today. Now, I promised you
last Sabbath that I would talk about the
10 days to better health. Before we get
started though, I want to say a word of
prayer and then we'll go ahead and talk
about 10 days to better health. So,
let's pray. Dear heavenly father, thank
you so much for this
opportunity to come together and to use
this amazing
technology to be able to spread the word
about this wonderful health message that
you have given us. And we ask you to be
with us. We ask you to bless this
wonderful program and that that all the
words that we share will be able to help
those who need to hear it and that these
words will be able to give them hope
that you have given us a message that
can bring health and healing to so many
of us. We ask you for your blessing in
Jesus name.
Amen. So thank you again for those of
you have to who have connected for being
here and uh I am so excited. I want to
tell you that the reason why I call this
10 days to better health
uh is because first of all before I
started this job that I currently have
I'll tell you a little bit about it.
Before though I started working in this
in my current job, I have been sharing
in my
ministry about
the Daniel what I call the Daniel
challenge for years. I want to say like
10 or 15 years. I have it in my website
and I want to share it with you. anyone
who wants to download a PDF that I have
in my website called the Daniel
Challenge. It's a 10day menu with
recipes, whole food,
plant-based. I call the Daniel Challenge
and I've had it for in my website for so
many
years. And this is something that I've
been teaching
forever, 10 days, because you know what?
It's in the Bible. Many, many of you
know that in the first chapter of the
book of Daniel in the Old Testament,
there's a story of young men, these
young men who were in
Babylon, who were actually in the court
of the king of Babylon. And they were
going to be trained to be, you know,
part of the court of Babylon because
they were, you know, found to be smart
and they were going to be uh trained and
uh they were going to be given the food
of the king. But these Hebrew young men,
they decided they were not going to
contaminate their bodies
uh with what they saw was the food that
was going to be given to them because
they already knew that God had given
them. And you know all of us that we
read the Bible, we know that there are
certain foods that we, you know, if we
want to keep our bodies healthy, we are
we are not to eat. And they already knew
that. And they decided not to
contaminate their bodies with the king's
food. And they were only going to eat
eat and if you read the Bible, it says
uh they were going to eat vegetable
foods and drink water. And uh the person
who was in charge of them was kind of
worried about them actually and said,
"Oh no." Uh you are not going to be very
strong and this is going to be terrible
for me. I'm going to get in trouble. And
Daniel in his wisdom said, "You know
what? Why don't you put us, you know, in
why don't you test us and see in 10 days
who's going to be
stronger?" And he said, "Well, okay.
Let's see what happens in 10 days." I
think he must have been somewhat
skeptical. Okay, let's see. 10 days. You
know, some there's some if you download
the PDF, it's in my website, by the way,
and it's I think it's already been put
there, so you can download it. Go to my
website. I actually in my website put
the the um references to some journals,
these uh articles in actual journals,
you know, like scientific journals.
There's these people who have written
journals who say that this story in the
Bible is the first uh controlled study
ever done in history because in 10 days
you had two groups that you can actually
compare and in a short amount of time
only 10 days you can actually see the
difference. You see like in science when
they do studies they have two groups.
Usually when they do control studies
they have two
groups and they in a certain amount of
time they compare those groups at the
end and they can see the difference and
if there is a difference and they can
see okay we did this experiment and we
found a
difference. Uh and Takara you and your
mom use a 10 Daniel the 10day Daniel
fast probably 10 days I assume and it
really works. Good for you. Good for
you. Because you know what? God has
given us these bodies and he has told us
how to how to best take care of them.
From the very beginning, as I mentioned
on Sabbath, from the very beginning,
first page of the Bible already tells us
how God designed our bodies with the
best fuel to put in our bodies. Right?
Just like when you go buy a a truck.
Let's say you go buy a truck at a dealer
and the truck is a, you know, diesel
truck. Are you going to put gasoline if
it's a diesel truck? You probably will
not because you know what's the best
fuel for that truck? And if you put the
wrong fuel, it's probably going to break
down. Same thing with us. We were given
a manual called the Bible. And in that
manual it says how to best take care of
this
body and how much more important this
body than a truck. I don't know what do
you think. So I'm going to start sharing
some slides with you
um about this presentation tonight. 10
days to better health and uh how the
biblical diet, what I'm going to call
maybe also the Genesis 129 diet, because
it's literally in the first page of the
Bible, just about every Bible, unless
it's really big print, it might be in
the second page, but most likely will be
in the first page of the Bible. Genesis
1:29. Just look it up. It says right
there what kind of uh diet was given
originally. Okay, originally the plan
had to change. Uh it was more likely
because of it, you know, it was almost
like an emergency situation because when
Noah came out of the ark, guess what?
How was the earth when Noah came out of
the ark? Was it in really good
condition? Do you think
after over a year of it being flooded,
do you think it was in really good
condition to actually, you know, eat out
of it? Probably not. So, in that
situation, there was an emergency
situation where God had to actually give
permission to human beings to eat animal
foods. But it was not the ideal. It was
not the original plan. The original plan
is it right there. Genesis 1:29. Plants.
That's the original. Okay. Now, let me
share with you something first of all
that I want to establish from the very
beginning. I might repeat this many many
times in other uh future presentations
because it's so foundational. It is so
important, especially nowadays, that
there's so much misinformation out there
that I really want to make sure that
both you and anyone else who watches
this in the future
knows that everything that I share and
that I want you to
know and and be sure that everything
that I am sharing is biblical. number
one and it that it is in harmony with
the spirit of prophecy that has been
given to us that I believe is a gift
from God. So the rule number one that I
always utilize for any presentation rule
number one is that everything that I
share with you will always be to the law
and the testimony that is found. This
verse you probably many of you already
know. Isaiah 8:20 says the following.
You probably many of you already know
this uh verse probably already you know
by heart to the law and the testimony.
If they do not speak according to this
word it is because there is no light in
them. So to
me it even just not just like biblical
concepts, theological concepts, but to
me this applies to health concepts. I
don't know if you agree with that, but
in my heart I think this applies to
health concepts. Everything that we hear
that we see YouTube, Facebook,
Instagram,
whatever you hear out
there, if it's not in
harmony, hear me out, please. if it is
not in harmony with the
Bible. And for those of you who are
Seventh Day Adventist, you know what I'm
talking about when I say the Bible and
the spirit of prophecy, the testimony of
Jesus, as the Bible says in in in uh
Revelation. It says the testimony of
Jesus is the spirit of
prophecy. If it's not according to this,
there is no light in it. And the reason
why I'm making so much emphasis on this
is because I see so much stuff right
now on social
media and I'm talking about within the
seventh day of this
church obviously outside of the church
is even worse. I mean, it's just like
there's all kinds of stuff obviously,
but I'm talking about unfortunately
uh there's so much much misinformation
being
spread. And the reason why I'm so making
so much emphasis right now is because
when we spread misinformation when it
comes to
health, it can harm people. That's why
I'm so worried about this. If we start
spreading things that are not
true, they might even harm people. I am
worried about this.
And it's our message. If we have 7th
Adventists, some of us who have been in
the church for decades and we don't know
our
message. I'm worried about that. You
know, how come we don't know our
message? I thought we did. you know,
some people I thought we we we did and I
guess maybe we have forgotten it. What's
happening? You know, so I think we
really ought to uh review our message or
go back to it and learn it again. I'm
not sure what's going on. So I'm going
to try to go back to the very essentials
of what is our you know maybe the
foundations of what God has given us
more so than ever to these times because
right now in these the last you know
times of earth's history it's becoming
more and more important. We'll be
talking about this throughout, you know,
maybe future programs today also maybe
and through future programs and why it's
so important maybe even so more in these
last days to be even more uh
knowledgeable and even following even
more more more the uh the health message
where it's so much more important even
today. Okay, so that's the first rule
number one. But the rule number two and
watch this. Okay, you might wonder why.
Okay, but I'll show you why. Rule number
two is to be ve okay. Oh, by the way, I
forgot that I wanted to show you the the
number two, the two texts that I think
are maybe very uh foundational, very
maybe very uh essential maybe for those
of you who really want to know about
health and and uh want to maybe know
what's written and the spirit of
prophecy as far as okay, how can I get
like a really quick, you know, um
summary of what uh the spirit of
prophecy says? about health. I would you
know recommend these two books uh
councils on food uh and diet and the
ministry of healing. These are books are
not very long especially ministry of
healing if you have never read it. I
think you can even read it for free.
Just download the app LG White read it
for free or buy the book at a store
online whatever. These are not hard to
read and they're just so beautiful.
Beautiful. So I would recommend you read
that. Okay. So the second thing I really
really want to
um the second principle I want to share
with you before we enter into the uh
health aspects of the of this of the um
of the diet is this science. And you
might wonder why why are we talking
about this? And it's because of this. If
we are not um sharing with others things
that are scientifically
valid, we might not we might lose
credibility. If we share with people who
are not Adventists things that are not
scientifically valid, we might share we
might lose credibility. We we're not
always sharing things with people who
are Adventist or Christian. So if we're
uh sharing things that are not always
validated with scientific um
evidence, people are not going to always
believe us. And um let me share
something with you. This is from Spirit
of Prophecy. Do you see what it says
right there about, you know, in the book
Christian Education, it says knowledge
is uh knowledge of science of all kinds
is power is power. And it is the purpose
of God that um advanced science is
taught in our
schools. Interesting. We should be
teaching science, real science in our
schools. So it's not God God is not
against science. I just wanted to let
you know. I just wanted to share with
you that we should not uh be against
science. We should actually uh look for
good quality science uh and share things
that are
good evidence. All right. Okay. So, I
just really w wanted to let you know we
should also in the Bible even says we
should really use common sense. We
should be wise as serpents and we should
be prudent. We should be prudent. We
should really not think in black and
white terms. Okay? Just wanted to share
those things with you before we get
going. All right.
Now these are the 10 leading causes of
death in the US. It has not changed for
so long. The only new thing in the uh 10
leading causes of
death is co. It's the only new thing
that has come up in the last five years
as you know. But other than
that and it's gone down because it it
got to up up to number three. It's like
the highest, you know, uh, place it got
and then it's gone down, but still up in
the first 10. But the number one never
changed. Number two never changed.
Number one is heart disease. Number two
is cancer. And of course, you have uh
strokes up there. You have diabetes. You
have Alzheimer's. You have all these
different diseases that have to do
with lifestyle for the most part.
And one of the most important parts of
lifestyle is diet. There's other things.
There's exercise. There's sleep. There
is stress. There's many things not just
diet. You can eat a perfect diet and
possibly not sleep or exercise or drink
water. And your health is not going to
be perfect if you are not doing those
things. Even if you eat a perfect diet.
But diet is probably the most important
thing because we eat uh more than we do
other things. We we usually eat at least
two three maybe four maybe more times a
day. Uh we are going to have uh
questions and answers at the end of the
program.
Now in the program that I do for work,
we measure certain things that you see
in the um on the screen. uh we measure
people's cholesterol actually we measure
people's lipid panel we measure their
cholesterol total cholesterol LDL
HDL we measure their
triglycerides all of this fasted by the
way in our little machine it's a
portable machine we're not very fancy we
don't have a lot of money but we do have
a little portable machine that measures
their lipid panel as well as their
glucose okay now if you go to your
doctor you'll probably get Another thing
maybe you might get your A1C that's a
little different than your uh fasting
glucose. A1C is more of a um an average
for 3 months where whereas the glucose
is that the measure for that one day. We
only measure glucose but we also measure
their blood pressure which is very
important and we measure their weight
and their height and we calculate their
BMI. All of this gives us an idea, not
very precise, but at least an idea of
what their risk might be for certain
diseases. CBD by the way stands for
cardiovascular disease. So that as I
mentioned in the previous uh slide is
the number one cause of death. So that's
why you know we look for that. Um, but
also there's other things like diabetes,
Alzheimer's, and you know, other things
that uh cancer that all of these things
might put us as a risk um for. And then
in our
program, we give them a
menu and we give them
recipes for 10 days. Right now, some of
these people have never
heard. This is completely new. A
plant-based diet. What? What are you
talking about? Never heard of this
before. Right. So, by the way, we these
recipes come with a QR code. We don't
have like tons and tons of money to be
printing 40 pages of recipes. So, we
give them QR codes. They look it up. You
know, there comes the recipe. We also
send them every day a little video. It's
only like three minutes just to kind of
keep them going. And it gives them a
tiny little bit of, you know,
motivation, a little bit of information
about not just diet, but also, you know,
a little bit of exercise, the sunlight,
you know, water, different things. Uh,
just every day I give them a call uh
during the week to see how they're
doing. Did you watch the video? You
know, do you have any questions? Uh, the
next Sunday, you it's on Sundays, by the
way, because people don't work on
Sundays usually, so it's easier than
during the week. Next Sunday, I give
them a a little class like this. talk to
them what I'm going to talk to you today
more or less the reason why all these
things happen all these diseases and how
they're all connected and the third
Sunday we do these um measurements again
that's it and what we see is amazing
honestly we do see
everybody improves at least one thing in
those 10 to 14 days honestly there's 14
days in between those two measurements
uh but everybody everybody study about
99% of people improve in at least one
thing but we've seen amazing amazing
results. Um some people improve like 50%
in like their LDL cholesterol. LDL
cholesterol is our best u biioarker is
what goes down the fastest in about just
about everybody. Total cholesterol is
the second one and glucose is the third.
It's just what we see uh improves the
best with this kind of uh intervention.
And I'll explain to you why right now.
I'm going to tell you why these are all
connected. Okay. So, what's the
underlying cause of all these metabolic
diseases? How are they connected? Well,
here's this is what I explained to
people the second Sunday. It's and and
once, you know, honestly, when I when I
um share this with people, I could see
in their faces that when they get it,
you can see in somebody's face when
they're like, get it, right? like I you
know I have the the the benefit of
actually seeing them live you know in
person and you can see that reaction in
people and it's you can see you can see
right there in their eyes oh wow okay
now I get it and that makes a huge
difference so what you see right now in
the screen is my little representation
it's very crude you know it's very
simple representation of a cell, a human
cell, very very simple drawing of a
human cell. And what you see right there
on the right, I think it's right hand
side of your screen page probably a G.
That G represents, as you see, glucose.
You probably heard the word glucose. I
hope, right? You have, right? Glucose.
You've heard the word glucose. Yeah, I
hope. Yeah. Tell me if you have. Please
put in the in the chat if you have
glucose. Now many people think glucose.
Oh, must be a bad thing. Glucose. Oh,
glucose almost scared of glucose. Well,
glucose shouldn't be scary because
glucose is fuel for your cells. We
talked about food as being our fuel.
Well, glucose is fuel for the cells.
It's absolutely
necessary. It's it's vital. The all the
cells need glucose.
The problem was when there's too much.
Yes, you have. Obviously. Yes. Thank
you. You have heard of glucose.
Everybody has heard of glucose. Now,
some people think glucose is a bad thing
immediately, but it's not. Glucose is
absolutely necessary. If you didn't have
it, you would die. But the problem is
when there
is too
much. How does that happen? Well, so you
see the G right there. That's a let's
say let's pretend it's a molecule of
glucose. Well, for it to work as a fuel.
Where does it have to go? It has to
go
[Music]
inside of that cell. It doesn't work if
it's outside, right? It's just like when
you put fuel in your car. Well, that
gasoline is not going to do any good if
you just spill it out on on the on the
floor on the concrete, right? It's not
going to work. It has to go inside the
tank. Same thing. This glucose has to
get in. Well, how does it get
in? Because do you see that thing around
that little pink thing around that
glucose? That's my representation of the
cellular. There's a membrane around the
cell. It It doesn't just let the glucose
in. You know, it's kind of like your
church. If you go into a a a church, you
know, when I teach this class, I do it
at a clinic and I tell my people, "Well,
this clinic when I got here in the
morning was closed. It, you know, I
can't just come in. Somebody has to open
it for me. And what do they need?" Well,
they need a key to get in. Well, same
thing with the cells. There needs to be
a door for that glucose to get in.
There's just no there's no free access
for glucose anyway.
It doesn't just come in. There needs to
be access to it like a door, if you
will. There's these receptors. Think of
them as doors, okay? The glucose doesn't
just come in. Somebody has to open the
door. So, when I go into the clinic in
the morning to do this program for, you
know, our participants, well, the
security person basically is the one who
opens the door with a key.
Well, who is the
key? The cell has mitochondria. Yes,
mitochondria. Takara, you're very right.
Mitochondria are like little furnaces,
right? That actually use up the glucose.
They're like the engine, if you will,
burn up this
fuel. All right, but first the glucose
has to get in. So, how does it get in?
Who opens the door? Who opens the door
with the key?
So many of you already know the answer.
Who opens the door? So I represented it
as this little
stickman. Do you know who it is? Oh, you
already probably can read it.
Oops. You read it, right? Oh, Takara has
already studied it. Good for you. You
already know all the answers. All right.
Well, the stickman is representing what?
Well, you already have the answer right
there, too. It's insulin. So insulin is
a hormone produced by that little organ
that you see right there too. Organ is
called the pancreas. So the pancreas
produces a hormone called insulin. And
one of the jobs of insulin is to open
the door just like the security man
opens the door for me in the morning.
They open the door and I can get in.
Well, insulin opens the door for glucose
to get in the
door, just like Takara said, to get in
and be used as the fuel. All right,
everything is going well so far. This is
all working as it should. This is how
it's supposed to
work.
But nowadays, things don't work as they
should because obviously there's
diseases. So, what's going on? Why is it
not working?
I'll tell you
why. Because
nowadays there is a problem. The problem
is Okay. Well, you already know. Well,
we have a problem with obesity and
overweight. Well, you know, we do not
live like our ancestors. As you already
know, our ancestors worked with their
bodies a lot more. They worked the land.
Many of them they, you know, when I do
this illustration with my participants,
many of their ancestors literally worked
the land, right? They
literally grew their own food and maybe
even cut wood to cook it. And the women
had to probably wash the clothing up out
in the river. I mean I take pictures uh
put to put them in my slides and women
washing clothes in the river and then
they carry them back. This is how people
used to do it. And so think about all
the physical activity that our ancestors
had to do just to live. They didn't have
to go to gym. They just did things and
that's how they, you know, kept their
muscle mass. They walked everywhere.
They just did a lot more activity and
they didn't have McDonald's, Burger
King, you know, Kentucky Fried Chicken.
So, they ate a much better diet. The
caloric intake wasn't even the same. I
mean, they didn't have a highly
processed foods that were highly
addictive. By the way, that's maybe a
topic for another day. The addictivity
of foods. Okay. So nowadays we have a
problem with 70% of our population is
either obese or has overweight. We
already know that the problem is not the
visible hear me out.
The problem is not the
visible, you know, love
handles. Those that's just visible,
right? Like the visible adapose tissue,
if you
will, that's not even the problem.
That's subcutaneous atapose tissue fat.
Okay, that's not that bad because it's
not the most dangerous fat.
Actually, the most dangerous fat is
invisible.
Did you know
this? The most dangerous fat number one,
visceral fat, is the fat that's actually
inside around the
organs. That's very risky actually. But
there's another type of fat. I don't
know if you've heard about this. I don't
know if you have heard.
There's a type of
lipids
called intra. Okay, here's a very
technical word. You don't have to know
this word, but I'm just going to name it
so that you can look it up if you want.
Intrammyiocellular
lipids. Fancy word. What is
intrammyiocellular lipids? Well, that
fancy word means fat inside the cell.
You can't see it. Totally invisible. You
don't even know it's there because it's
inside the cells. You don't see it. You
don't know it's
there. But that fat inside the cells
does not
belong. Now, why does it get
there? Because we eat too many calories
and we don't burn
them. You see what I'm saying? too many
calories, not burning the calories well.
So they this, you know, extra calories
accumulate in several places, the
subcutaneous fats, all those love
handles. Okay, there's that. But also
the internal fat that puts you at a
higher risk for metabolic disease. No
bueno. And then there's the fat inside
the cells,
intrammyiocellular lipids. Well, what's
the problem with
that? the extra fat inside the cell. Do
you see what's going on here in this uh
in this little drawing that I made? It's
blocking the what
now? What is it
blocking? What's blocking? It's blocking
the door, you guys. It's blocking the
door. That's the problem. Takara, thank
you. She knows. She's already studied
that. She said she
knows this is the
problem. The extra
fat inside the
cells blocks the door. It's as if you
put a chewing gum in the hole where the
key
goes. So, what happens if you can't put
the key inside?
You go in and try to open the door. Can
you get
in? You can't get
in. So
now, is it because you don't have the
key though? Is it lack of insulin the
problem? No, it's not lack of insulin.
See, there's a misunderstanding
sometimes that diabetes comes because
there's no insulin. There is insulin. At
least at the beginning, there's plenty
of
insulin. There's plenty of insulin. The
problem is the insulin doesn't work
because there's something blocking
it. There's something blocking the
insulin. You see what I'm saying? Not
lack of insulin. Is insulin not working
because something is blocking it. What's
blocking it? What's blocking
it?
Intramiocellular lipids. The word lipid
is fat. Lipid equals fat.
It's this fat inside the
cell. Where where does it come
from? Either the fat we eat or the fat
we carry. Because there's skinny
people. There's skinny people. Yes or
no? Is there skinny? Are there skinny
people who also get diabetes who also
get high um blood pressure or high
cholesterol? Does that happen?
Yes, it
happens. Why? Because a person who is
thin or can also eat a highfat
diet. It seems like it they can eat
everything they want. They don't gain a
pound. But how's the health inside of
them? How's that? How are their
sales? See, they can be paying the price
of that down, you know, 10 10 20 years.
I don't know. I don't know. All right.
So, here's what's going
on. The pancreas sees this little uh
mess going on here and
saysoop, you know, red
alert. I need to figure out how to help
this this situation. So, what can the
pancreas do? Well, it just pumps out
more insulin, more
stigmen, more keys. Is that the problem
though? Was the problem lack of
keys? Lack of stickman. That wasn't even
the problem to begin with. So, you know,
the illustration is not 100%. You know,
so it actually what happens is it does
help a tiny little bit. So, it's almost
like you're trying to force some of the
insulin through the windows, let's say.
All right. So, you know what?
your blood sugar does come down tiny
little bit because by the way okay so I
forgot to tell you something so if this
insulin is not going inside the cell
well where is it staying
then if it's not going inside the cell
where is it if it's not inside then
it's outside what's where is outside
what's
outside what's outside where do you
think it's
outside. What's outside, you guys? This
is outside. People come into our
clinic,
fasted. Sunday morning, they haven't had
breakfast. We take a little tiny little
drop, put it in the little
strip. What should be a good fasting
glucose?
M let's see what if the fasting glucose
is 105. What do you
think? Is that
good? No bueno. Yes, Nicole. Thank you.
It's in the bloodstream. If it's not
inside the cells, it's in the
bloodstream. So, we take that little
blood drop, put it in the strip.
Whoops. It's in the bloodstream. It's
not inside the cells where it should be.
So what does the pancreas do when this
situation starts to happen? The pancreas
goes in red
alert. So at the beginning of the
situation when this is starting to
happen, the pancreas tries to tries to
help. All right? And how does it try
what what does it do to try to help? It
pumps out more insulin. So this this um
situation when the uh pancreas pumps out
more insulin is called hyperinsulinemia.
You can actually go get tested for this
hyperinsulinemia. So what happens is
well there's all this insulin in your
body and some of that block glucose does
come down.
So, okay. So, maybe you don't have
diabetes
yet. So, maybe your blood sugar is not
150. Maybe it's
98. Maybe it's 98. So, okay. So, let's
say you go to the doctor and it's
98 or
97. So, what if you went to the doctor
tomorrow? Fasting glucose 97. What would
the doctor say to you or the nurse or
whoever? What would the doctor tell you
if your blood sugar is
97? Someone
97. 97. Come on. Is it good, bad,
normal, high? Pre-diabetes, diabetes,
what? Someone. What's
97? Tell me.
97 is I'm
waiting. What's 97? Pre-diabetes. No
bueno. GG's like, "Oh, what is 97?" I
don't
know. What's 97? Is it normal? What
would the doctor say? Good, Deborah.
Thank you. The doctor will say,
"Good. Guess what? You don't have
pre-diabetes. You don't have diabetes."
Oh, good. Go home. Keep doing what
you're
doing. All good.
Is it okay? Look at this slide. Are you
looking at the
slide? Is this all good? Is this normal
to you? Like does it look Well,
obviously it's not. This is not exactly
what's happening. It's all like not
cartoony like that inside your body,
right? But the pancreas pumping out
extra insulin, your glucose not going
in, all the fat inside the cells.
Is this
good? Is this good? Does this look
normal to
you? How can this be good? But the
doctor says, "Oh, it's good." The nurse,
PA, whatever, nurse practitioner,
they'll tell you normal. Whatever you're
doing, keep doing it. All good.
Congrats. What?
Huh? No. What's going on here? I'll tell
you what's going on. This condition,
look at this. Okay, look at this,
please. This condition has a
name. This condition, Takara already
said it, you guys. I don't know if you
read it. I don't know if you're keeping
up with her
comments. This condition has a name.
It's
called insulin resistance.
insulin resistance. Why? Because the
insulin is right here. It's not lacking.
It's there. It's not lacking. Okay? The
insulin is there trying to do its job,
but it can't. It's not working. Why
isn't working
again? Why isn't it
working? Do you see this here? This
yellow
blob. What's the yellow blob
again? The fat.
Is it the Coke that you
drank? Is it the extra
cookie? Cuz that's another
misunderstanding. It's only the sugar
that causes the diabetes. Nothing else.
You can have all the fried chicken you
want. It will not give you
diabetes.
What? You see, there's so many
misunderstandings here. Now, I'm not
saying the Coke's not going to it's
going to be any good because all that
coke, all that sugar, it's going to go
into the liver. The liver is going to
make it into fat. Yes, the sugar becomes
fat in the liver. No
bueno. But it's not only the sugar. See,
that's what I'm trying to tell you.
There's more to it, right? The fat also
can do this because fat doesn't need to
be converted to fat. The fat is already
fat. The sugar becomes fat. The fat is
fat. No
bueno. Both of them are no
bueno. Now, what are we going to do you
guys? Here's another picture just from a
textbook. This is more like the
classical textbook picture, not my
drawing. But you see here, normal cell,
insulin resistance, and here are the
block channels, the closed doors
basically where the glucose cannot go
in. But I want to show you this one.
This one has the yellow blobs. You see
them? These yellow balls basically. And
right here's the technical word right
there. Intramiocellular lipid. Now you
can go home. Well, you are home. You can
actually look it up. Okay. If you in
case you're you know what what is this
in my cellular you can look it up okay
well I want to tell you that this whole
insulin resistance
thing is not just for
diabetes what you see in the screen in
the screen and maybe uh it can be blown
up I don't know if it can be make any
bigger so that people can actually see
the uh the words more
closely but I want to tell you that um
insulin resistance has much it's has
many more complications than just
um than just diabetes. It's actually
related to a whole
host
of diseases as you can see. you see that
all the different types of diabetes.
There's I don't even have time right now
to explain what type diabetes type 1.5
is honestly because there's diabetes
that is related to your eating and
there's diabetes that has actually to or
your lifestyle has diabetes actually is
um autoimmune diabetes and diabetes type
1.5 is an autoimmune diabetes. Then
there's, you know, pre-diabetes,
gestational diabetes,
cancer,
cancer, coronary artery disease, and
there's just all these things. I can't
even read them honestly because I'm it's
too small for me. Let me see.
Hypertension, aththerosclerosis,
obesity, high cholesterol, fatty liver
disease,
PCOS. I hope you know that. PCOS is poly
uh polycystic uh ovary uh syndrome
Alzheimer's disease uh neuropathy
blindness that's that comes from the
retinopathy up here kidney failure
blindness erectile dysfunction type 1
diabetes all of these
things insulin resistance goes way far
beyond just diabetes do you see all of
these things are related that's why I'm
telling you Everything is connected.
Atherosclerosis, hypertension, cancer,
Alzheimer's disease. By the way, look up
the the term type three diabetes. If you
don't believe me, type three
diabetes. I'll just tell you what it is
because you know we're here. Type three
diabetes, Alzheimer's disease.
Alzheimer's disease. Type three
diabetes. Because the researchers have
found that you can have insulin
resistance in the
brain. The liver
becomes fatty when it's
resistant and then it has high
cholesterol, high glucose, high
fat. So now you have hyper lipidmia,
hyper cholesterolmia,
hypoglycemia. And this uh this excess
cholesterol goes all over the place and
it starts to accumulate inside of the
vessels and now you have inflammation.
Now you have to take statins and now you
have fatty liver. Oh my goodness, it's a
huge mess, right? It's a huge mess. It's
all connected. I just wanted to
establish that it's all connected.
That's why the same food and the same
diet helps everything. But this is the
cause. It's excess fat and we're not
burning the fat. We're eating too much
fat. We're accumulating too much fat.
We're not burning it. So it's lack of
exercise. So it's a lifestyle. Now I
want you to see this table. Maybe take a
picture. So take out your phone and take
a picture. This is from the uh book
Goodbye Diabetes from Dr. Wes Youngberg
from Lumal Linda. I haven't seen this
table anywhere
else. Uh, and it's wonderful because it
doesn't just show the
pre-diabetes, advanced pre-diabetes, and
then the diabetes, right? We already
know this. The doctor tells you this
stuff after, you know, 126 fasting
diabetes. If you have more than 100
fasting, it's pre-diabetes.
And he actually breaks it up into
advanced pre-diabetes. That's great.
That's awesome. But look at this. Nobody
tells you this stuff over here. You see
what I'm saying? He says high blood
sugar, stage one, stage two. What? What
is this? Why does it call it high blood
sugar? Why?
Well, because he noticed when he worked
with people in Guam, actually, he went
to Guam and he worked with young people
who were already suffering the
consequences of high blood sugar without
having diabetes or pre-diabetes, but
they were having the high consequences
of insulin resistance, at least levels
of fasting blood sugar. And he realized,
well, these people have insulin
resistance because their blood sugar is
higher than optimal. You see right here,
optimal. This is the optimal. If you go
above 84, well, what's going
on? You might already have high blood
pressure or high cholesterol, high
triglycerides, or something else. It's
because you might have insulin
resistance. So, take a
picture because nobody else is going to
tell you this unless you buy the book.
Good. buy the book, Goodbye Diabetes.
You might find it at the ABC or just
order it online, probably. All right, so
there's this. And then there's another
um even better one that I think he
partnered with some people and came up
with this one. Wow, this is amazing, you
guys, because this one shows you the
risk increase. Wow, look at you guys.
increase heart uh disease risk at stage
two meaning at fasting blood sugar
starting even minor actually it starts
at
see minor and then it starts to really
come up here
95 because there's already insulin
resistance
there. That's why we have to start
paying attention
early. That's why the food is important.
Now, talking about the number one cause
of death, this was found in the 90s. Dr.
Dean Ornish found that a lowfat
vegetarian diet along with exercise,
stress
management, also they had to stop
smoking if they did smoke. But up until
the 90s, they thought if you had
coronary artery disease, you could never
get rid of it. Once you had it, you had
it forever. But he put people on a diet,
stress management, and exercise. Look at
the difference. This is before and this
is after. Now, what we're looking at
here is a artery. And what we're seeing
inside is the plaque. And do you see the
difference here? they were able
to start to lower the artery. Okay, so
with the diet, you can start reversing
heart disease. That's amazing. And you
can see here that maybe taking out the
meat, putting beans and soy in your diet
can help. Wow, that's great. Same here.
Okay, so I just wanted to show you. It's
been found in many um studies now back
almost 100 years ago. Blood pressure
here in the United States, they think,
"Oh, it's normal to have blood pressure
when you're old. It's just normal. It
happens. It's normal. It has to happen.
It just happens." Okay. But 100 years
ago in Africa, they went and just went
to these, you know, very uh rural places
in Africa. And what did they find? What
did they find? Look at the age groups.
15, 20, 25, 30, 40, 50, over 60. And
look at the blood pressures. 123, 122,
126, 126, 125, 118, 113, 109, 106, 105,
and diastolic 81, 79, 83, 84, 85, 81,
70, 70, 60, 66. What's going
on with ages going what?
down. It's the opposite. But by the way,
they're comparing with Europe and North
America which going up. You see 125 13
140 12 13 12 13 12 13 12 13 12 13 12 13
12 13 12 13 12 13 12 13 to 140. Same
with diastolic going up in Africa going
down. It's the opposite. So does blood
pressure really have to go up with age?
Is it
normal? It doesn't have to go up with
age. And now we're tell they're telling
us guess what plant-based diet can
actually treat
hypertension diabetes. Oh, I forgot to
tell you by the way Dr. McDougall did a
study where they in seven days. Look at
what they found. Seven days. This is
blood pressure.
Okay.
1,615 people. At the beginning of the
seven days, the average was 1590 over
94. at the end. 136 over 83 in just 7
days. Whole food
plant-based. And by the way, you want to
also, we talked about this salt. You
want to reduce the salt because it can
prevent 22% of fatal strokes and 16% of
heart attacks. Where's the salt? Oh
boy. Oh boy. Oh boy. Here are the things
where the salt is found. By the way,
they put chicken. You know that raw
chicken has salt in it? Did you
know? I wanted to show you something.
They put salt in raw
chicken. They inject
uh salt water into chicken. I don't know
if you knew that. Okay, these are all
other terrible, terrible foods. They
have way, way, way too much sodium. Too
much. Okay, diabetes. I wanted to show
you this is just the standard you know
ADA diet. They force us nutritionists to
give people this diet practically but in
two weeks they measured uh the results
of the plant-based diet compared with
the ADA diet. This diet is based on
portions portion portion portion. And
this diet you can eat as much as you
want
basically. And after two weeks, this
group had more weight loss, more
reduction in the glucose, and no portion
control. They could eat however much
they want. The only difference was the
proteins. So instead of eating the
usually the 88 diet is white meats over
here, beans, tofu, that kind of stuff.
So that was it. That was the difference.
Now we tell people try to eat low
glycemic. In other words, carbohydrates
that don't elevate the blood sugar.
That's what we tell our participants.
And as far as triglycerides, that's the
another thing we measure and we tell
people to stay
away. This is just basically junk food.
Honestly, stay away from junk food
because it will elevate. Sugar is number
one that elevates triglycerides and
other things, you know, alcohol of
course, you know, other other
medications that also there's some
medications that elevate
triglycerides
and that's what you want to be under
150. Um, but especially and I mean we've
had people that have over 500. So
triglycerides are not as dangerous as
cholesterol,
but we don't really want high
triglycerides. So what to do to avoid
high triglycerides? Stay away from the
sugar number one
and eat a low glycemic
diet. So this is what we recommend. This
is basically the bottom line. We tell
people eat a lot of
fiber. So whole grains, legumes. Legumes
are the beans. Eat all the beans you
want. In fact, I recommend people,
especially if they have diabetes or
pre-diabetes, to eat half a cup of beans
in every meal. You know why? Because the
beans are the number one source of
fiber, especially soluble fiber. And
that fiber helps to keep blood sugar at
a stable level all throughout the day.
So, people with diabetes and
pre-diabetes benefit very much with
having a half a cup of beans in every
meal. lots of fiber, fruits and
vegetables. In fact, I don't know if you
remember that that plate that I showed,
half the plate really should be fruits
or vegetables. The plant proteins again
come from the legumes, but and by the
bean, by the way, soy is a bean, so
that's also a legume. And the green
vegetables by percentage all honestly
have a lot of um on a lot of protein. We
tell our people to eat try to not eat a
lot of like a lot a lot of bread
because they do have a lot of you know
um we we do have a lot of participants
who are uh diabetic. So if they eat more
of the whole grains like the quinoa and
you know that kind of thing it will help
not to elevate their blood sugar so much
because we only had them for 14 days. So
we try to help them as much as possible.
The fats, one ounce a day. Avocados and
nuts and seeds are what we try to really
um
emphasize. And we only can, you know,
give them a good diet, but we try to
tell them to also incorporate things um
with lifestyle. And this is really the
only type of eating pattern that helps
with everything. you know all the
different conditions all of them it
covers all of them and the only side
effects are good so what can I say you
know there's really no better diet so
the two principles are to try to take
away all the processed foods so sugars
flowers too much oil
especially fl you know white flowers and
the animal foods we really asked them to
for the 10 days to stay away from all
animal foods. It's really hard for
people to really get it because most
people don't even know. Uh they're not
they're not used to this. This is
completely new for a lot of people and
they don't even do it. Honestly, a lot
of people don't follow it 100%. But even
if they follow it 90%, they still get a
benefit. Uh that's what we see anyway.
So this is the diet that God has given
us. Whole food plant-based. It's
beautiful. It attracts the eyes because
God has given us colorful fruits and
vegetables. The colors are pigments and
the pigments are
antioxidants. That's why they're so
attractive to us. They are the beautiful
colors that God has given us. And again,
the proportions I really try to tell
people to eat half of the uh plate
fruits or vegetables. I want to end with
this um this verse that comes from John
10:10. I came so that you may have life
and live it more abundantly. Honestly,
that's what God wants for us. He's not
giving us a just a set of rules so that
we can just follow the rules just you
know and and so that we can have a
boring life you know and just let get
get less uh joy out of it. It's the
exact opposite. When we incorporate
these healthy habits we actually get
more joy out of life because we feel
better. And I have people who have done
my program four times, five times, six
times, seven times. They keep coming
back even though our program, you know,
says, "Oh, stay away from this. Stay
away from that." But they keep coming
back because they feel better. That's
all I wanted to share with you. They
feel better. So, thank you. Sorry, I
kind of went over time, but I just get
so I get so excited.
Um, I really want to thank you for for
staying here and um, I hope this was
helpful. I will try to share with you at
least twice a month uh, some more
information. I want to um, invite you to
download from my website the
10day Daniel challenge. This is my own.
I have been given uh permission from my
boss to also share the one we have. It's
a collection from her recipes, my
recipes and just recipes from uh forks
over knives and other places. So if you
really want uh just write me on my
website there's a contact
um page and you can just write me and
I'll just share you the other there. You
can have two sets of 10 days basically.
But I hope you try it because in 10 days
you can feel
better because I've seen it. So I know
you can. I don't know if we have still
time for questions, but I'm definitely
open for it. If you guys want to go over
a little bit, um I'm totally fine with
it. So yes, I am open for
it. How much protein and fiber should a
person have? Well, that will depend. Oh,
how much protein and fiber should we
have a day? And chickpea pasta is good.
Chickpea pasta is definitely good for
diabetes. Yes, absolutely. Absolutely.
And how much protein? That will depend
on the age, the height, the weight, you
know, it just depends, but usually um
they recommend at least 30
32 grams of um of fiber. Most people
don't get nearly that much. Most people
eat like half. So, everybody should be
eating more more fiber honestly. And the
protein will depend on your weight, but
most people really if they eat uh a lot
of legumes every day, whole grains every
day, vegetables every day, they will
probably get enough protein. Somebody's
asking, okay, well, let me see. How long
does nutrition last in the body? Is it
true that sweating means you actually
burning fat?
Well, if you're sweating, you are
consuming calories. So, the I have to
say that it depends whether you're
burning fat or not. If you just ate food
recently, you're probably going to be
burning a lot of carbohydrate, meaning
you are burning mostly carbohydrates at
first. If you do exercise in the
morning, fasted, you're going to burn
fat. I can almost guarantee that. If you
do intermittent
fasting, you're going to burn a lot of
fat. I can guarantee that. So, try
intermittent fasting. Eating twice a
day. And early timerestricted eating
when you eat more in the morning and
less in the evening is one of the best
ways to burn fat. I can guarantee that.
I have tried that and I a lot of people
have tried it. If you do that in
conjunction with a whole food
plant-based diet, it's almost impossible
not to lose weight.
Really? All right. Uh, eggs. Okay. Well,
it depends. Um, it's better than eating
pork. It's better than eating red meat.
I can say that for sure. The egg yolk is
the number one source of cholesterol in
the diet. It's very, very concentrated
in cholesterol. I was reading a study
yesterday about cholesterol. Cholesterol
doesn't really, the cholesterol in the
egg yolk will probably not elevate serum
cholesterol. In other words, the
cholesterol in the diet doesn't really
elevate your cholesterol, but it has
other
uh other consequences in the body. For
instance, they have found that dietary
cholesterol for instance can have
consequences as far as the risk for
cancer. That's one of the things. So,
and protein the the uh animal protein
itself can elevate the risk for cancer.
So, you know, I don't recommend it
necessarily.
I think we should try to I have a whole
uh topic on just um on just eggs and
dairy. So one day maybe I'll do that
I'll do that presentation if you guys
are interested in just just eggs and
dairy. Uh so that's another one maybe
for the future. I thought tofu was on
the list to not eat. Actually tofu is
one of the most is one of the healthiest
foods probably in the world. Uh, and the
blue zones are the five regions where
people live the longest. And one of
those regions is is Okinawa, Japan. And
they eat a lot of tofu actually. And
they're one of they are the longest
living people in the world actually. So
what can I say? Tofu is very you here in
the United States, all the tofu is GMO
free because otherwise people wouldn't
buy it. So all the tofu you're going to
buy is G is non GMO by the way. Uh so as
long as you buy non-GMO soy, you're
going to be fine. And they have found
that soy is prevents cancer. I've been
writing as uh for a person who asked me
to contribute to a book on cancer and
I've written a whole chapter about
10,000 words on cancer and nutrition.
And I've written a whole bunch on the
myths of soy and and debunk a lot of
that. And I have to tell you that soy is
a food that helps to prevent cancer. In
fact, it's wonderful to prevent cancer.
They have found that men who drink at
least one or two um um glasses of soy
milk uh have 71% less risk of of um
prostate cancer. And women who eat soy
foods have less risk for breast cancer.
Women who have had breast cancer and eat
soy food have less chances of it
returning. And women who are going
through menopause who eat half a cup of
soy cooked soy beans, not tofu, not soy
milk, but I mean you can eat that too.
But the cooked soy beans help to lower
all those menopause symptoms by
84%. Half a cup of soybeans, 84%
reduction. If you're going through
menopause, you probably might consider
that. FYI, it does not have estrogens.
It has phytoestrogens which are not ex
the same at all. In fact, they modulate
estrogens in the body. In other words,
if you have too much estrogen, they bind
to estrogen receptors in your body and
help to lower the binding of those
estrogens in your body. So, it helps to
lower the the uh effect of real
estrogens in your body. If you don't
have enough, it helps to increase, you
know, the, you know, the the good u
benefits of estrogen in your body. So,
it's a estrogen modulator. What has real
estrogens like actual estrogens, not
pseudoestrogen or phytoestrogens, what
has real estrogens is dairy milk because
the cows are impregnated when they're
being milked. So when you drink milk,
you're you're actually drinking actual
estrogen. When you eat soy, you are
consuming um estrogen modulator that
helps you when you have excess estrogen
or when you don't have enough estrogen.
That actually helps you in both cases.
FYI, what else? I think we have to go.
Gigi's telling me we have Oh, please get
the questions on the uh please get the
questions on the screen.
Ah, I don't know how to do that. Oh, the
question's on the screen. Okay. Can a
person do anything about
gallbladder short of gallbladder
removal? Yes. Probably drink a lot of
water. Stop eating a lot of cholesterol.
Most of the gallbladder uh stones are
made out of
cholesterol. So, you want to not eat any
cholesterol at all. And yeah, drink a
lot of water. Change your diet
immediately to a anti-inflammatory diet.
[Music]
Um, and no fat. Like lower your fat
immediately. Go into a lowfat diet now,
yesterday, right away. Is there a diet
for MS? Yes, there is. There is. Um, in
fact, this is what I would tell you.
Short story um because we don't have a
lot of time. Go into Dr. Michael
Greger's page because he has done a lot
of videos on this. Michael Greor. Dr.
Michael Greger and his page is
nutritionfacts.org.
nutritionfacts.org. He has done a lot of
videos on this and there is a protocol.
It's basically a whole food plant-based
diet, but he has also shown the studies
on how you know there is this um doctor
who did a whole bunch of research on
this and yeah that basically you can
control MS long term years. I mean
basically this doctor had like these
patients who lived perfectly well for
years and years. I mean he did like 10
years of followup, 20 years followup, 30
year followup and the the patients were
doing fantastic. So yes yes yes you can.
So do it do it. Uh can you shrink uh
thyroid nodules? I think it depends on
the the cause. I think you have to look
at the cause. Any suggestions autoimmune
conditions? Yes. autoimmune conditions.
You guys follow Dr. Brooke Goldner. Look
her up on YouTube. Look her up on
Facebook. She has a book. First of all,
she had lupus and she basically cured
her own lupus. She's an MD. And then she
wrote the book Goodbye Lupus. And then
she wrote the book Goodbye Autoimmune
Diseases because she started helping her
own patients too who had autoimmune
diseases, other autoimmune diseases. So
look her up. Uh she has free videos. She
helps I don't think she has time to help
people oneonone anymore because she has
way too many people who follow her. So
she does like group classes and things
like that. But just read her book and
it's basically an autoimmune um
protocol. The number one thing she does
is she eats a lot of greens. Just you
drink a huge green smoothie every day
because those green vegetables are very
very anti-inflammatory. Green vegetables
are very anti-inflammatory. So you eat a
huge salad and then you green you eat a
or drink a green smoothie because how
else are you going to get so many greens
into your body? So, you do that and you
also eat a lot of flax and chia because
flax and chia are very anti-inflammatory
because of those omega-3 fatty acids.
But how are you going
to then have an anti-inflammatory
um effect if you keep putting
pro-inflammatory foods into your body?
It's not going to work, right? It's just
not going to work. can't just be putting
pro-inflammatory foods and try then to
lower the inflammation. So, you really
kind of have to go into an
auto-inflammatory diet, which is a whole
food plant-based diet, but you go the
extra mile. So, you add a lot more
things and and basically it's a lot of
greens and it's a lot of flax and chia.
You have to, you know, lower your
stress, sleep a lot, drink water. I mean
all of this stuff it has to be a whole
lifestyle I would follow her. We can
talk about some other day I can do an
auto autoinflammatory or autoimmune
anti-inflammatory topic someday. Uh when
a person is trying, this is going to be
our last one. I was told um when a
person is trying to heal from a
disease, especially autoimmune diseases,
do you believe staying away from foods
high in acid?
Yes. Eating more alkaline? Yes. High in
carbon H2? Yes. So, yes. The um Yes.
Yes. Yes. Absolutely. So the whole food
plant-based diet is alkali alkanizing
because you're going to stay away from
the most acid forming foods in the diet
which are animal proteins. Uh now there
are some plant protes that may produce
some acid but in the in the whole like
in the
aggregate the plant-based diet in
general will not be acid acid forming.
So you will be alkalinizing your body in
general. So you will not be losing
calcium for instance which people who
eat up uh eat based meat-based diet
produce too much acid leech calcium out
of their bodies that's how you end up
with osteoporosis for instance. So yes a
plant-based diet in general in the
aggregate will alkalinize your body.
Yes, that's what you want to do. Eat
more plants. Eat more plants. So yes
100%. So thank you very much for being
here. I am going to pray now and end
with a word of prayer. I just want to
thank you so much again for staying here
being with me, putting up with me
because I talk too much. Um, but you can
uh I'm going to start putting these
videos up on my own channel because I
don't have a lot. I just have way too
many in my Spanish channel. But I'm
going to start putting more in my
English channel, but go to my website
down download the 10day uh plan. Start
doing it. And if you have any questions,
just hit me up on my uh on my website
and I'll try to do these at least twice
a month. And just if you have any
questions, I'll probably cover um some
of the stuff you have questions on. So,
but I do have some topics, you know,
that I can also do in case you don't
have any questions. So, let's
pray. Dear heavenly father, thank you so
much for the opportunity to get together
to have this program. Thank you for all
the people who uh connected tonight.
Thank you for just the knowledge that
you gave that you give us for the
opportunity you ha that you give us to
learn so much about the body, the human
body, the physiology and how everything
works. And thank you for giving us this
wonderful message of healing, of
salvation. Thank you Lord for giving us
the Bible, the spirit of prophecy where
we can learn so much about how to better
take care of this temple uh of your Holy
Spirit. Help us Lord. We know we're
addicted to so many things. Help us to
better take care of our bodies. Help us
to spread this knowledge to those who
are suffering from so many
diseases. This world is so sick. Help us
Lord to take this message to others so
others may know that you are our healer,
our doctor, our savior. Thank you for
everything in Jesus' name.
Amen. Thank you again you guys. We'll
see you in the